Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf officially 33, we pick
up ל"ב עמוד א'. Lamed Bet Amud Aleph. We pick up towards
the bottom and we pick up with the following: והשתא
תנו רבנן. V'hashtah Tanu Rabbanan. It's about the middle of the page,
about six lines after the גמרא Gemara begins. And we are dealing
with the case about about this issue about somebody who, again, two
brothers, two sisters,
and that even if the one of and then one brother dies,
so she's אחות אשה, achos isha,
and then even if the second guy's wife dies, she remains אחות
אשה. achos isha. Okay, nothing too new from what we've seen, but
now although not so much new in the משנה, mishna, the גמרא
Gemara is going to introduce a ברייתא braisa which is going to
get us on a major discussion taking us in a very different
area. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, about six
lines below where the גמרא Gemara begins on ל"ב עמוד א'. Lamed
Bet Amud Aleph. בא עליה, ba aleha,
let's say, forget this whole fancy case, a man basically
married somebody, a person's brother married his wife's sister. All right, and
then the guy died. Let's even assume, thank you, let's even assume
no יבום, yibbum, who knows there were kids, forget יבום. yibbum. So
this is a woman that's both this man's brother's wife and wife's
sister. Two prohibitions. And he has sex with her. What's the story?
בא עליה חייב עליה משום אשת אח ומשום אחות אשה דברי רבי
יוסי. ba aleha chayav aleha mishum eshes ach umishum achos isha divrei
Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says a reasonable thing, he transgressed
two prohibitions: it's both his brother's wife and his wife's sister. Fine.
רבי שמעון אומר אינו חייב אלא משום אשת אח בלבד. Rabbi Shimon
omer eino chayav ela mishum eshes ach bilvad. No, he only transgressed
brother's wife, he doesn't transgress wife's sister. Why not? She is both.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ותניא, v'tanya, so before we even analyze
it, first we have to deal with the contradiction. רבי שמעון אומר
אינו חייב אלא משום אחות אשה בלבד. Rabbi Shimon omer eino chayav
ela mishum achos isha bilvad. You only transgressed wife's sister. So רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon clearly has an idea that you're only going to
transgress once. But first of all why, and second of all, according
to one version it's only brother's wife and the other version it's
only wife's sister, and this woman is both. So what's the explanation?
So now that we'll reconcile this problem we'll see what the reason
behind it is. So the גמרא Gemara is, לא קשיא. lo kashya.
כאן שנשא חי ואחר כך נשא מת. kan shenasa chai v'achar kach
nasa mes. In one case, first the surviving brother married her, and
then the dead brother, not when he was dead, but who now
is dead, married her. And in the other case, כאן שנשא מת
ואחר כך נשא חי. kan shenasa mes v'achar kach nasa chai. It
was the reverse. What does that mean? It means, and again, no
יבום, yibbum, I'm not talking about יבום yibbum for today, believe it
or not. We are talking about brothers and sisters but we're not
talking about יבום. yibbum. Okay? So you've got, okay, everybody has kids
let's say, okay? Don't worry about יבום, yibbum, everybody's got kids. All
right? So you've got ראובן Reuven who's married to רחל Rachel and
שמעון Shimon is married to לאה. Leah. And ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon are happily married with tons of kids, ראובן Reuven dies. Okay?
So רחל Rachel is both אשת אח eshes ach and אחות אשה.
achos isha. Okay? And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you only, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon only transgresses one if he sleeps with רחל. Rachel.
Why? So it says here's the difference: ראובן Reuven is the מת,
mes, the guy who eventually dies, okay? So if first ראובן Reuven
married רחל, Rachel, before they were married, what does רחל Rachel become
first to שמעון? Shimon?
אשת אח. eshes ach. Then שמעון Shimon marries לאה, Leah, so רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you go by the first definition. Why? We'll
see, אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. So
she's only אשת אח. eshes ach. That's if נשא מת ואחר כך
נשא חי, nasa mes v'achar kach nasa chai, she's אשת אח. eshes
ach. Let's say it's the reverse. שמעון Shimon is first married to
לאה, Leah, okay? What is רחל Rachel now to שמעון? Shimon? אחות
אשה. achos isha. Then he marries her, so she remains אחות אשה.
achos isha. So that's נשא חי ואחר כך נשא מת. nasa chai
v'achar kach nasa mes. Okay? So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you,
he only gets the first definition, which is a concept of אין
איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. One status of
prohibition does not take effect on top of another one. And so
which one takes effect? The one that was there first. Okay, this
is the first one, the second one does not take a place
on top of the first. So it goes all by the first
status. So that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's idea that there's only one,
and the contradiction is which is the one that was first. All
right, so let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. So
this is what we're going to be into for all of today.
No יבום, yibbum, the question of אין איסור חל על איסור. ein
issur chal al issur. What? Are they both כרת? kares?
Are they both כרת? kares?
Yes, they're both כרת. kares.
So what's the difference?
Oh, so good question, yeah, you're going to hell either way. The
difference is if it were בשוגג, beshogeg, do you bring one קרבן
korban or two קרבנות? korbanos? Okay, and there might be other differences
too, but that's an excellent point, yes.
Does אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al issur apply
those examples where it's like יום כיפור Yom Kippur a guy eats
בשר בחלב basar bechalav all piled up on top? Yes.
Okay, so or I should say maybe, but those are part of
the discussion. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this. לא קשיא כאן
שנשא חד ואחר כך נשא מת כאן שנשא מת ואחר כך נשא
חד.
lo kashya kan shenasa
chad veacharch nasa meis kan shenasa meis veacharch nasa chad. רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon says the גמרא. Gemara. Now רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon who
says only one. היכא דנשא מת ואחר כך נשא חד.
heicha denasa meis veacharch nasa
chad. First the dead guy, Reuven married her. So she began by
being אשת אח. eishet ach. And then he married Leah, so then
it was אחות אשה. achos isha. כיון
דאיסור אחות אשה לא חייל, keivan deissur achos isha lo chayeil, since
Rachel never became אחות אשה, achos isha, תתייבם מיבמי? tisyabem miyabmi? So
we've got a question. How according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon this
is a classic case if there are no kids where there's no
מצות יבום mitzas yibbum because Rachel's an ערווה. erva. Says one minute,
according to רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon why is Rachel an ערווה? erva?
Okay, he first marries Rachel, then he marries Leah. You're telling me
Rachel is only אשת אח eishet ach because that was her first
status. So now if Reuven dies with no kids, go ahead and
do יבום yibbum with Rachel. She's not your wife's sister, she's only
אשת אח. eishet ach. Okay.
That's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay. Because as
soon as you allow for יבום yibbum then אשת אח eishet ach
goes away and then she becomes אחות אשה. achos isha. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רב
אשי, amar Rav Ashi, איסור אחות אשה מכתלא תלי וקאי. issur achos
isha miktala tali vekay. It's not like wife's sister is not a
relevant concept, it's hovering above. Okay,
it's an appropriate status, it just can't take effect because there's a
pre-existing one. So therefore אי פקע איסור אשת אח, ee paka issur
eishet ach, if the status of wife's brother would go away- of
brother's wife would go away because there would be a מצות יבום,
mitzas yibbum, so then אתי איסור אחות אשה וחייל, asi issur achos
isha vechayeil, then she would all of a sudden become now wife
sister
and that prohibition would apply. So you can't do יבום. yibbum. יבום
yibbum would turn her into an ערווה. erva. והלכך לא פקע vehilchach
lo paka and therefore because it can't go away because it would
just invite the next one, it doesn't go away. Okay, which interestingly
then also means that you know then the sister- then the other
wives are צרת ערווה tzaras erva and all these things, even though
right now she's not an ערווה, erva, but because she would become
an ערווה erva were there to be a מצות יבום, mitzas yibbum,
there's no מצות יבום. mitzas yibbum. And therefore she remains the איסור
ערווה issur erva of אשת אח eishet ach even when there are
no kids. All right, so that's fascinating in itself, that type of
mechanism. But now we're going back to the issue of איסור חל
על איסור. issur chal al issur. וסבר רבי יוסי איסור חל על
איסור? vesavar Rebbi Yossi issur chal al issur? So now רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yossi says he has both definitions. So does רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yossi really hold that one איסור issur takes effect on the other
one? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braisa, עבר עבירה שיש
בה שתי מיתות. avar aveira sheyeish bah shtei misos. If somebody did
a sin that has
two death penalties. נידון בחמורה. nidon bachamura. So then the question is
it's like a סנהדרין Sanhedrin type of a question, which is which
of the מיתות misos do you give? There are ארבע מיתות בית
דין arba misos beis din and some are seen as more weighty
than others. So the הלכה halacha is if somebody did a sin
and is deserving of two, you give them the more weighty death
penalty. רבי יוסי אומר נידון בזיקה הראשונה הבאה עליו. Rebbi Yossi omer
nidon bezika harishona habaa alav. No, you go by the first relationship.
There's that word זיקה zika again. תניא, tanya, then we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, כיצד, keitzad, what how would this play out? אמר
רבי יוסי נידון בזיקה הראשונה הבאה עליו. amar Rebbi Yossi nidon bezika
harishona habaa alav.
So חמותו ונעשית אשת איש. chamoso venaasait eishet ish. Now a mother-in-law
is punishable by שריפה, sreifa, which is a weighty death penalty. אשת
איש, eishet ish, a simple case of adultery is punishable by חנק,
chenek, which is considered a less weighty form of execution. Okay, so
חמותו chamoso is the weightier one. So according to let's say a
woman is both a man's mother-in-law and a married woman. That's an
easy scenario, right? His mother-in-law is married, so to his presumably his
father-in-law. So anyway in that case she's mother-in-law and a married woman.
So the תנא קמא tanna kamma would say, so he gets punished
by שריפה sreifa because that's the weightier- the mother-in-law status is the
weightier one, is the weightier death penalty. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi says
no, only by the first way the relationship was defined. What does
that mean? כיצד נידון בזיקה הראשונה הבאה עליו? keitzad nidon bezika harishona
habaa alav? חמותו ונעשית אשת איש. chamoso venaasait eishet ish. Let's say
she first was his mother-in-law and then she became a married woman.
How could that be? His wife's mother was divorced or widowed, so
first this woman was his mother-in-law and then she got married. So
the first definition that she had to him was mother-in-law. So in
that case he gets punished by שריפה. sreifa. Okay.
אשת איש ונעשית חמותו. eishet ish venaasait chamoso. If it's אשת איש
eishet ish and she became his mother-in-law, which is also a very
reasonable scenario. This woman was married and then he married her daughter.
So first this woman was a married woman before he ever right
got married to her daughter, she was forbidden to him as a
married woman and then he married her daughter. So in that type
of a case the first status is married woman, mother-in-law comes later.
So in that
case נידון באשת איש, nidon beeishet ish, then it's then he's punished
by
אשת איש. eishet ish. So he says basically the only logic to
say give the weaker one is because you are saying that the
other one doesn't exist. I mean the only the only logic allowed
him to say חנק chenek and not שרפה sreifah is because he
says you're not punishable by שרפה, sreifah, right? Because if you really
were both you'd get the more serious punishment. So clearly he is
saying, and that's the language, נידון בזיקה ראשונה, nidon be'izka rishona, this
is an idea of אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal
al issur. We're not going to define it as both prohibitions, we're
going to define it as the first prohibition, the one that first
defined your relationship to this woman. So now we've got this problem.
The same רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that says a woman who is
wife's sister and brother's wife is both punishment, both definitions, says that
a woman who is married woman and mother-in-law is only goes by
the first definition. So which one does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose say?
Does he say איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur or
אין איסור חל על איסור? ein issur chal al issur? So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abbahu,
מודה רבי יוסי באיסור מוסיף. modeh Rabbi Yose be'issur mosif. All right,
now we're getting into the real sort of heart of the discussions
of איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur. There are two
ideas, actually three that we're going to do today.
I have, thank you. So there's איסור מוסיף, issur mosif,
which is,
okay,
איסור כולל issur kolel
(doesn't
mean it's אסור assur to go into a כולל), kollel and בבת
אחת. bas achas. Okay, בבת אחת
bas
achas we're going to deal with later. בבת אחת bas achas just
means that you don't, you can't say the first one because they
take, because they both took effect at the same time. Okay, so
we won't worry about that right now. איסור כולל, issur kolel, איסור
מוסיף. issur mosif. What is the difference? All right, איסור כולל issur
kolel means it is of, it broadens the scope. You've got something
that's forbidden, the second איסור issur came along and that actually made
this person, thing, object, whatever, forbidden to a wider scope of people.
So for example, let's talk about mother-in-law and married woman. Which, do
they have equal scope in terms of the people that they are
that that are forbidden? No. Married woman is אסור assur to who?
Everybody.
Mother-in-law's only אסור assur to son-in-law. So if it started with mother-in-law
and then became married woman, right, so then that's a איסור מוסיף,
issur mosif, מוסיף mosif is the broader scope. More people. And
that could take effect. If it started with married woman
and
then became mother-in-law, that's a narrow scope that doesn't take effect. Okay,
so that actually would, so that's what we're saying. Now how does
that solve it? Because we're not trying to solve the mother-in-law case,
we're trying to solve this case. Okay, so let's talk about it.
Brother's wife and wife's sister. Which one has the broader scope?
Well, it depends, I mean doesn't one דחיא, dechaya, right?
No, no, that's duration. That's not scope. Brother's wife. Brother's wife is
forbidden to the other brothers as well. Okay, so how could רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose say here that you get both? Well, it depends
on the order. If it first started with wife's sister, that's a
narrower scope. Then ראובן Reuven married רחל, Rachel, she became forbidden to
all the brothers, that's a broader scope, that's an איסור מוסיף issur
mosif and then it could also be both. So you could get
both here if the order was first wife's sister and then brother's
wife. So okay, that there רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, the reason רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose says both is if you did it in this
order.
Only in the case of more than one brother?
If the case is two, I mean, so the גמרא Gemara seems
to not care whether in practice there are more brothers. Anyway, another
brother could be born. At least conceptually it's a prohibition that applies
to a broader scope of people. Okay, but that's a good point,
but the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to care. So why can he
say both here? Yes, generally אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur
chal al issur unless the second one has broader scope. So you
could get two here if the order started with אחות אשה achos
isha and then she got married to the brother and then it
got broaden. In the case of mother-in-law and married woman, right, if
mother-in-law came comes,
if married woman comes first, you're never going to get him, mother-in-law
is the weightier one, you're never going to get him for mother-in-law
because married woman is already the broader scope. So that's why he
says you'll never punish the guy by שרפה sreifah if married woman
comes first because mother-in-law is a narrower scope it won't take effect.
But in this case you can get the guy for both as
long as wife's sister comes first then brother's wife is broader and
then that you can get him for both.
Yeah, so just want to make absolutely sure you've been defining איסור
מוסיף issur mosif not איסור כולל. issur kolel.
Correct, we haven't got to איסור כולל issur kolel yet.
Okay, so let's put that away. איסור מוסיף issur mosif is more
people. More people, right, broader scope
of people prohibited.
Okay, all right, so let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara says now. Yes.
So the reason doesn't take, is not accounted for here because let's
say you divorce her.
Correct. For now we are not going to worry about things like
duration, severity, okay? It's complicated enough as it is, so we're going
to go with so far what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so
let's take a look.
Okay. מודה רב יוסי באיסור מוסיף. Modeh Rav Yossi b'issur mosif. תינח,
Teinach, and says fine, that will work, היכא דנסב חייא ואחר כך
נסב מת. heicha d'nasav Chayya v'achar kach nasav Meis. First,
the surviving brother, whatever, Shimon married, so it started by being wife's
sister, and then the guy who's going to die married
her, and then she became brother's wife. So if it starts with
wife's sister and then becomes brother's wife, that's a larger scope, then
you have both. מיגו דאתוסף איסור לגבי אחים, Migo d'itosaf issur legabei
achim,
since now Rachel is forbidden also to all other brothers, so אתוסף
איסור לגבי דידיה, itosaf issur legabei deidei, so she also becomes forbidden
once already this new status, here's a way of conceptually thinking about
it. The new status takes effect on Rachel because it has relevance
to other people. It might not have relevance to Shimon, she was
already אסור assur to Shimon, but it has potential relevance to other
people, either brothers or brothers who might be born. Okay. Now Michael's
going to ask what if the father is dead so there are
no brothers could be born, my mother is dead, fine, doesn't matter.
In theory, okay, it has relevance to other people, and because this
new status has relevance to other people, it also has relevance even
to Shimon, even though she was already אסור assur to Shimon. Okay,
that's איסור מוסיף. Issur Mosif. Okay. So that works if she started
as wife's sister and then became brother's wife. אלא היכא דנסב מת
ואחר כך נסב חייא, Ella heicha d'nasav Meis v'achar kach nasav Chayya,
was reversed. First she was brother's wife and then she was wife's
sister, so why in that case would רב יוסי Rav Yossi say
that you get both statuses? מאי איסור מוסיף איכא? Mai issur mosif
ika? Wife's sister isn't adding any prohibitions. Okay, she's already brother's wife,
אסור assur to all the brothers, or any, not prohibitions, any people.
וכי תימא, V'chi teima, maybe you'll say מיגו דאיתסר בכולהו אחוותא, migo
d'issar becholhu achvasa, maybe,
ah,
here's what happens. She started off as brother's wife and then Shimon
married Leah. So now she is forbidden to, not she is actually,
Shimon is forbidden not just to Rachel, but now that Shimon married
Leah, who else is Shimon forbidden to? Any other sisters.
Any other sisters that might exist. And of course there might not
be any other sisters, again, that doesn't matter. In theory, Shimon now
by marrying Leah is אסור assur in more, in all sisters. Now,
that's not the same. That's not saying Rachel used to be married
to this scope of אסור assur to this scope of people, now
she's אסור assur to a wider scope of people, right? That's איסור
מוסיף. Issur Mosif. It used to be a narrow scope, this new
status makes her forbidden to a wider scope. Rachel is not אסור
assur to more people. She was אסור assur to all the brothers,
she remains אסור assur to all the brothers. But if Shimon marries
Leah, now there is a, now there is, now like Shimon is
אסור assur to all sisters, okay, all sisters of Leah. So the
fact that now Shimon becomes אסור assur to all other sisters of
Leah, can he also now, well once I'm being אסור assur to
all sisters I should be אסור assur to that sister as well
even though he was already אסור. assur. That's not איסור מוסיף, Issur
Mosif, that's איסור כולל. Issur Kolel. Okay, so איסור מוסיף Issur Mosif
is you start with the forbidden thing, okay, it has a narrow
scope, and then the איסור מוסיף Issur Mosif comes along and says
it's now going to have a broader scope of people that it's
אסור assur to. You start with the forbidden
thing, okay. איסור כולל, Issur Kolel,
I'm having too much fun with my markers and their
colors, okay, anyway, your
איסור כולל, Issur Kolel, what's איסור כולל? Issur Kolel? איסור כולל Issur
Kolel is that you basically have here, right, Rachel
and here's Shimon, okay. So Rachel remains just as, you know, she
started, she started, right, by being forbidden here to, right, all the
brothers. She was אשת אח, eshet ach, these are all the brothers.
Okay, that's where you started, okay. Then Shimon goes ahead and marries
Leah, right, he goes ahead and marries Leah, he now is אסור,
assur, Shimon until now was אסור assur just to Rachel, now that
he's married Leah, he's also אסור assur to all the sisters.
Okay, right? So you see the difference, right? Here, Rachel herself that
was אסור, assur, at the second stage became אסור assur to more
people. Since she's אסור assur to more people, right, in this scenario
where first she was a sister, a wife's sister and then a
brother's wife, because she became אסור, assur, right, to more sisters, here
she was just married to, here she was just אסור assur to
Shimon, and then she became אסור assur not just to Shimon but
to all the brothers.
Why is that?
Okay, because first, first she was wife's sister. Right, once she
then be married the brother, she wasn't just אסור assur to שמעון,
Shimon, she was אסור assur to all the brothers. So she now
is אסור assur to more people, so now she gets a status
of brother's wife to the other brothers, she'll get the status of
brother's wife even to שמעון. Shimon. That makes a lot of sense,
right? Because what happens is she married the brother, she's considered brother's
wife to these other guys, so she's also gonna be considered brother's
wife to שמעון. Shimon. So that's adding the scope, broadening the scope
to who she's אסור, assur, therefore applying it to שמעון. Shimon. This
is less obvious. Okay, here her status hasn't changed. She was אסור
assur to all the brothers, she remains אסור assur to all the
brothers. Okay, her status hasn't changed. What has changed is שמעון Shimon
used to be אסור assur just to her, and now he's אסור
assur to all the sisters. So since these other sisters are now
forbidden to him, right, should we say that since they're forbidden to
him, she should become forbidden to him as well with this new
definition?
She becomes part of a larger כלל. klal.
She becomes larger of a כלל, klal, right.
יתר מוסיף, yeter mosif, it's a larger כלל, klal, broadening.
No, her status, her, she is not אסור assur to anybody more
than she was אסור assur before. Okay, so her status has not
changed. People to the left and right of her have changed. Her
sisters now are אסור, assur, and she's part of her sisters. So
does the fact that her sisters are אסור assur also sweep her
away and make her considered to be in that status as well
and אסור assur with that new definition? This is clearly more obvious.
Her own status changed, right? She started off just being אסור assur
to שמעון, Shimon, then she married the brother, and now she's אסור
assur to all the brothers. That's a new definition that directly applies
to her, that impacts the other brothers. If it's a new definition
that's true to her now, brother's wife that has relevance to other
brothers, let it have relevance to שמעון Shimon as well. Here her
whole status has changed. Here her status didn't change, her sisters' status
has changed. But since her sisters' status have changed and she's part
of her sisters, maybe that'll make her status change as well. Yes.
If you look at it from רחל's Rachel perspective, this is exactly
backwards, right? I mean what is איסור מוסיף issur mosif for him
is איסור כולל issur kolel for her. Because she,
he becomes part of a larger כלל klal of people that...
no, because in this case she's not אסור assur to any more
people. Meaning if you're asking who can she have sex with, before
she couldn't have sex with the brothers and now she can't have
sex with the brothers.
Now this doesn't affect her because שמעון Shimon was still...
the different, yeah, yeah, yes. In other words the איסור מוסיף issur
mosif רחל Rachel has now become אסור assur to more people, right,
איסור כולל issur kolel רחל Rachel now finds herself amongst a larger
population of people who are participating in the same...
correct,
exactly. Okay. All right. Now we got those. If you got those,
you are so far ahead of the game.
I don't need forbidden to go to a כולל. kolel.
Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: וכי תימא, u'chi tema, lest you say, מיגו דאיתוסף בכולהו אחוותא,
migu de-itosef bekula achvassah, now that there was שמעון Shimon married the
sister, all of the sisters are now forbidden to
שמעון, Shimon, האי איסור כולל הוא, hai issur kolel hu, that's an
איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, that's an איסור כולל, issur kolel, and therefore
why should that create a double status? She's not new אסור assur
to more people, just other people in her כלל klal are אסור.
assur. So אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, רבא Rava says, you
know what, you're right. So of course we could have said maybe
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose holds of איסור כולל, issur kolel, but
then it wouldn't work for the whole case of mother-in-law and married
wife, etc. So we're stuck, right? So how do you explain why
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says both cases, so the גמרא Gemara that
you get both statuses of wife's sister and brother's wife. So אלא
אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, מה לי אני עליו כאילו עשה שתים
ואינו חייב אלא אחת. mah li ani alav k'ilu asah shtayim v'eino
chayav ela achas. So רבא Rava says you know what, okay fine,
you're right. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would hold in the reverse case,
you really would only get, because he really only holds of איסור
מוסיף, issur mosif, he doesn't hold of איסור כולל, issur kolel, because
that's clear because of the case about mother-in-law and married wife, there
are cases where you only get the married wife status and you
don't get the second status. So he's not gonna hold you can
sort of get the second thing to count one way or the
other. So why by the case of brother's wife and wife's sister
does he say you transgress both? He doesn't mean literally. He doesn't
mean technically in terms of the actual punishment we'll impose, like two
קרבנות korbanot or two series of lashes or two death penalties. Okay,
he doesn't mean that in that way you did both. He means
you deserve to get punished for both, it's as if you transgressed
both. Of course like what type of a halachic statement therefore is
that? What type of a meaningful statement is that at all?
Right? מה לי אני עליו כאילו עשה שתים? mah li ani alav
k'ilu asah shtayim? So then what way is he actually even arguing
with רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says oh it's
not like you transgressed two things. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says it
is like you transgressed two things. Who the heck cares? What does
it change? like mean anyway, right? So one way of thinking about
what this means is, right?
If I strip the idea of punishment from it, let's pretend that
there was never any punishment in the תורה, Torah, right? Would I
say you transgressed two עבירות aveiras or not? Okay, when we say
אין איסור חל על איסור, Ein issur chal al issur, does that
mean that you literally didn't transgress the prohibition of wife's sister? I
mean she's your wife's sister. No, you didn't transgress it? Or do
we say you transgressed it, but maybe there are no consequences to
it. The halachic consequences are all defined by the first status. So
whatever the consequences might be, lashes, a קרבן, korban, you know, a
certain type of a death penalty, that doesn't, that all is defined
by the first status. So but maybe even if we say אין
איסור חל על איסור, ein issur chal al issur, maybe you still
are transgressing just without consequences. That might be what this means. Okay,
but this now becomes a weaker answer. We have ר' יוסי Reb
Yosi by the case of mother-in-law who is married woman and he
says you only get one. We have the case about sister-in-law who's
also wife's sister and he says you get two. So the גמרא
Gemara says if it's in a certain order I can understand why
you get two. If it's in the other order I can't understand
it. And the גמרא Gemara then says, alright, you're right. You really
don't get two in that other case, but it's like you get
two. מה לני ליה כאילו עשה שתיים. Mah lani leh ke'ilu asah
shtayim. Very interesting answer. וכן כי
אתא רבין אמר ר' יוחנן מה לני ליה כאילו עשה שתיים ואינו
חייב אלא אחת. V'chen ki ata Ravin amar Reb Yochanan mah lani
leh ke'ilu asah shtayim v'eino chayav ela achas. מה נפקא מינה? Mah
nafka mina? So the גמרא Gemara does not like this idea of
it's as if you. Who cares as if, what does that mean
anyway? And if he's arguing with ר' שמעון, Reb Shimon, there's got
to be some relevance to the discussion. So מה נפקא מינה? Mah
nafka mina? לקוברו בין רשעים גמורים. Likavro bein reshaim gemurim. The נפקא
מינה nafka mina is to bury amongst fully wicked people. Okay, because
based on how much of a רשע rasha a person is depends
on where they get buried in the cemetery. ובפלוגתא, Uv'plukta, now because
there's a whole issue that somebody you know when בית דין Beis
Din executes somebody the more weighty punishments they get buried in one
section, when they execute him the more lighter executions he gets buried
in another section. So this guy is treated, if you want to
use the Brisk-er terminology, בגברא, b'gavra, in terms of his like personal
status and identity, as if he did two עבירות. aveiras. Even though
in terms of the actual punishment and consequence of that act he's
not going to get punished, but in terms of what it says
about him as a person it is like there are two. Again
very funny and what exact type of debate that is with ר'
שמעון Reb Shimon is not exactly clear. Okay, but what we have
introduced is the idea of ר' שמעון Reb Shimon saying categorically אין
איסור חל על איסור, ein issur chal al issur, ר' יוסי Reb
Yosi saying there are times you could have איסור חל על איסור,
issur chal al issur, and the גמרא Gemara identifying those times as
when it is an איסור מוסיף, issur mosif, when the second one
broadens the scope that that first person was forbidden to. Now that
person is forbidden to a broader scope of people and therefore the
status changes for that even with the second איסור. issur. Yes?
Just like imagine אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al
issur the following way. This is actually it's like items in a
vending machine. They're stacked on top of each other. You can't get
at the second one until
the first one is gone. That's a way of thinking about it
certainly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, ובפלוגתא,
uv'plukta, this issue,
this issue of איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur and
איסור מוסיף issur mosif etc. is connected to another debate. And let's
take a look, and this hopefully will read pretty quickly. דאתמר, De'itmar,
it was taught, זר ששימש בשבת. zar sheshimmesh b'shabbos.
You have a non-כהן Kohen who works in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash on שבת. Shabbos. Now what's the normal הלכה halacha about a
non-כהן Kohen who works in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? חייב מיתה,
Chayav misa, okay, at least בידי שמים. b'yedei shamayim. What's the normal
הלכה halacha about somebody who does מלאכה melacha on שבת? Shabbos? חייב
מיתה, Chayav misa, בידי אדם b'yedei adam actually. So here he goes
and he works in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash on שבת. Shabbos.
Is he חייב מיתה chayav misa twice? Because of a non-כהן Kohen
who works in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and doing as a
non-כהן Kohen he's not allowed to work, if he were כהן Kohen
he could work in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash on שבת. Shabbos.
As a non-כהן Kohen he's not allowed to. So he's חייב מיתה
chayav misa for חילול שבת, chillul Shabbos, or only one? So let's
take a look. זר ששימש בשבת. Zar sheshimmesh b'shabbos. ר' חייא אומר
חייב שתיים. Reb Chiya omer chayav shtayim. בר קפרא אומר אינו חייב
אלא אחת. Bar Kappara omer eino chayav ela achas. קפץ ר' חייא
ונשבע. Kafatz Reb Chiya v'nishba. ר' חייא Reb Chiya jumped up and
took an oath and he said העבודה, HaAvodah, which is a very,
it's like cute because עבודה avodah means the service in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but it's also a way of taking an oath.
Okay, by the service, by the divine service.
כך שמעתי מרבי שתיים. Kach shamati meRebbi shtayim. That if someone, if
a זר zar serves in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash on שבת
Shabbos he's חייב chayav twice. קפץ בר קפרא ונשבע. Kafatz Bar Kappara
v'nishba. בר קפרא Bar Kappara jumped up and took an oath. העבודה,
כך שמעתי מרבי אחת. HaAvodah, kach shamati meRebbi achas. I took an
oath he said I heard the exact opposite from רבי, Rebbi, only
one. That was one debate. התחיל ר' חייא לדון. Hitchil Reb Chiya
ladun. So ר' חייא Reb Chiya said let's try to figure this
out. Okay, we got two opposing opinions, nobody's backing down, let's try
to figure it out. Okay, let's use, let's be reas, let's use
some reason here. שבת לכל נטרה. Shabbos l'chol nitra. שבת Shabbos is
forbidden to everybody.
כשהותרה במקדש, K'shehutzra b'mikdash, when it was permitted in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, you don't have to worry about שבת, Shabbos, אצל כהנים
הותרה. etzel kohanim hutzra. הותרה. hutra. It was said for Kohanim, Kohanim
get a dispensation.
לכהנים הותרה ולא לזרים. L'kohanim hutra v'lo l'zarim. The dispensation only applied
to Kohanim, not to non-Kohanim. So this person is transgresses both for
a non-Kohein who does the Avoda and for Shabbos, he never got
a dispensation. Okay? יש כאן משום זרות ויש כאן משום שבת. Yeish
kan mishum zarus v'yeish kan mishum Shabbos. So he says, that's my
logic, that's a pretty reasonable- forget taking oaths, that's a- that's my
logic, that makes sense. יצחק בר כפרא Yitzchak bar Kappara says, okay,
let me tell you my logic. שבת לכולא נאסרה. Shabbos l'chola nasra.
Shabbos was forbidden to everyone. כשהותרה, K'shehutra, when it was- when a
dispensation was given, במקדש הותרה, be'Mikdash hutra, not for Kohanim. The Halacha
was מלאכה הותרה melacha hutra on Shabbos in the Beis HaMikdash. Which
is pretty funny, I mean, Rebbe Chiya's position makes more sense. What,
anybody can come- I can come into the Beis HaMikdash and start
making a fire?
But the only people that can do Avoda are Kohanim.
I know, but this is a non-Kohein, right?
I understand, like any- but by definition, this person is not doing
Avoda, is what he's saying.
I know, but Bar Kappara is saying he's only חייב אחת chayiv
achas because anytime you're מחלל שבת mechalel Shabbos in the Beis HaMikdash,
it's a dispensation. It's very bizarre, right? He's saying you're only חייב
אחת. chayiv achas. I can go to the Beis HaMikdash, light a
match, oh, well, the Beis HaMikdash there's no איסור שבת. issur Shabbos.
All right, so
exactly. So yeah, I mean, Bar Kappara is very strange. שבת לכולא
נאסרה כשהותרה במקדש הותרה. Shabbos l'chola nasra k'shehutra be'Mikdash hutra. In the
Beis HaMikdash, no problem of Shabbos. אין כאן אלא זרות. Ein kan
ela zarus. So if a non-Kohein does the Avoda, it's only a
non-Kohein doing Avoda. Forget the Shabbos problem, Shabbos in the Beis HaMikdash,
no problem. Very strange. Okay. By the way, this does not sound
like it's about איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur. It
sounds like it's about how conceptually we understand what does it mean
that the איסור issur of Shabbos was waived in the context of
עבודה. Avoda. Okay? But now we're going to see three debates that
are in parallel. Okay? And seems to be a broader sort of
philosophy is informing all of them. All right, so let's take a
look. בעל מום ששימש בטומאה. Ba'al mum she'shimish be'tuma. You have a
Kohein that has a מום, mum, a blemish. It's אסור assur for
him to serve in the Beis HaMikdash. Then he became טמא. tamei.
It's also אסור assur for a טמא tamei person to serve in
the Beis HaMikdash. Okay? Now this already more sounds like איסור חל
על איסור issur chal al issur because we're dealing with the איסור
issur to serve in the Beis HaMikdash, is it אסור assur in
one direction or in two directions? Okay? So let's take a look.
רבי חייא אומר חייב שתים. Rebbe Chiya omer chayiv shtayim.
Rebbe Chiya again says, boom, you get both. בר כפרא אומר אינו
חייב אלא אחת, Bar Kappara omer eino chayiv ela achas, only one.
קפץ רבי חייא ונשבע העבודה כך שמעתי מרבי שתים. Kafatz Rebbe Chiya
v'nishba ha'avoda kach shamati me'Rebbe shtayim. Right,
by the divine service, this is what I heard from Rebbe, you're
חייב chayiv twice. קפץ בר כפרא ונשבע העבודה כך שמעתי מרבי אחת.
Kafatz Bar Kappara v'nishba ha'avoda kach shamati me'Rebbe achas. Okay, I
heard- I took an oath only once. התחיל רבי חייא לדון. Hischil
Rebbe Chiya ladun. Fine, let's discuss it. טומאה לכולא נאסרה. Tuma l'chola
nasra. טומאה Tuma was forbidden to everybody. כשהותרה במקדש K'shehutra be'Mikdash now
the part that I didn't mention, which makes this more parallel to
the Shabbos case, is it's
a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. Okay? So טומאה tuma is allowed in
the Beis HaMikdash for a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. So if he
was a normal Kohein, he'd be allowed to bring the קרבן ציבור
בטומאה, korban tzibbur be'tuma, right? Okay, but the problem is that he's
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. So it's similar to the idea of
Shabbos, which is that were you a normal Kohein, you would have
a dispensation. Because you're a בעל מום, ba'al mum, you don't. So
therefore do you also transgress the prohibition of טומאה? tuma? So let's
take a look.
Okay. טומאה לכולא נאסרה. Tuma l'chola nasra. טומאה Tuma for- you know,
doing עבודה בטומאה Avoda be'tuma was forbidden to everybody. כשהותרה במקדש לכהנים
תמימים הותרה. K'shehutra be'Mikdash l'kohanim temimim hutra. When it was given a
dispensation because it was a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, that dispensation was
given to the Kohanim who could do the עבודה. Avoda. לכהנים תמימים
הותרה ולא לבעלי מומין. L'kohanim temimim hutra v'lo l'ba'alei mumin. The dispensation
was only to Kohanim who could do the עבודה, Avoda, not to
a בעל מום. ba'al mum. So for him, the prohibition of טומאה
tuma still applies, even though it's a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. יש
כאן משום בעל מום ויש כאן משום טומאה. Yeish kan mishum ba'al
mum v'yeish kan mishum tuma. So you have both prohibitions. התחיל בר
כפרא לדון. Hischil Bar Kappara ladun. Bar Kappara says, let me argue
it. טומאה לכולא נאסרה. Tuma l'chola nasra. טומאה Tuma was forbidden to
everyone. כשהותרה במקדש במקדש הותרה. K'shehutra be'Mikdash be'Mikdash hutra. When it was
allowed because of קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, it was allowed for anything
in the Mikdash. And now this, by the way, makes a little
more sense than Shabbos. To say on Shabbos I can walk into
the Beis HaMikdash and strike a match seems crazy. To say the
idea of טומאה הותרה בציבור, tuma hutra be'tzibbur, when there's a קרבן
ציבור korban tzibbur we waive טומאה tuma concerns and we allow קרבנות
korbanot to be brought, there there is- it makes some sense to
say, based also on those other discussions in the גמרא Gemara that
we saw, that we sort of like ignore the fact that there's
טומאה tuma once you're bringing a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. And then
maybe it's not- if anybody were טמא tamei or did the עבודה
Avoda or whatever, it would not be an additional prohibition of טומאה.
tuma. We're sort of like ignoring the problem of טומאה tuma given
that it's a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur.
The קרבן korban doesn't become טמא? tamei?
Well, it does, but you can still be מקריב makriv it. The
prohibition is waived. Okay. Wait, let me see. טומאה לכולא נאסרה כשהותרה
במקדש במקדש הותרה. Tuma l'chola nasra k'shehutra be'Mikdash be'Mikdash hutra. In anything
done in the Beis HaMikdash, טומאה tuma by a קרבן ציבור korban
tzibbur we're ignoring it.
אין כאן אלא משום בעל מום. Ein kan ela mishum ba'al mum.
Let's say it is coming from the כהן kohen, *kohen*. Let's say,
I don't know, everybody is טמא tamei. מת *tamei mes* or something.
There was a war and everybody got טמא tamei מת *tamei mes*,
or everybody whatever, so all the כהנים *kohanim* are טמאים *tmeim*. Okay,
but it's a קרבן korban ציבור *korban tzibur*, it has to be
brought.
So the question is what's the distinction between, they're arguing whether a
כהן Kohen *kohen* who is טמא tamei *tamei*, who is already טמא
tamei *tamei*, can bring.
No, a כהן Kohen *kohen* who is טמא tamei *tamei* can bring
a קרבן korban ציבור *korban tzibur*. But let's say this כהן Kohen
*kohen* who's טמא tamei *tamei* is also a בעל מום Ba'al Mum
*baal mum*, so he's excluded anyway from bringing קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*. Okay,
so he transgresses being a בעל מום Ba'al Mum *baal mum* who
does the עבודה avodah *avodah*. Does he also transgress being a טמא
tamei. *tamei* person doing the עבודה avodah *avodah*? Or in this context,
טומאה *tumah* is irrelevant? Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this, third case. זר zar
שאכל מליקה Melika *Zar she'achal melikah*. So you go ahead and the
כהן *kohen* does the, brings the קרבן korban. *korban* of the bird,
the bird חטאת *chatas*, and he uses his fingernail to pierce it
from behind
the neck. Now, if that were not a legitimate קרבן korban. *korban*,
it would be a נבילה neveilah *neveilah*. It would be a bird
that died without a kosher שחיטה *shechitah*. So this person now is
a non-כהן *kohen*. It is a kosher קרבן korban *korban*. A כהן
*kohen* did it and brought it and it's a kosher קרבן *korban*.
He, but it can only be a חטאת *chatas*, it can only
be eaten by כהנים *kohanim*. He's a non-כהן *kohen*. He's not allowed
to eat a חטאת *chatas*. He goes ahead and he eats this
חטאת *chatas* bird. He certainly transgressed eating a חטאת *chatas*. Did he
also transgress eating נבילה neveilah *neveilah*? Because it is a נבילה neveilah
*neveilah*. Okay. So זר zar, שאכל מליקה Melika *Zar she'achal melikah*. רבי
חייא rabbi chiya אומר חייב chayav שתים *Rabbi Chiya omer chayav shtayim*.
בר קפרא bar kappara אומר אינו חייב chayav אלא ela אחת *Bar
Kappara omer eino chayav ela achas*. קפץ רבי חייא rabbi chiya, ונשבע
העבודה כך שמעתי מרבי שתים *Kafatz Rabbi Chiya venishba, haavodah, kach shamati
meRabbi shtayim*. קפץ בר קפרא bar kappara ונשבע העבודה כך שמעתי מרבי
אחת *Kafatz Bar Kappara venishba, haavodah, kach shamati meRabbi achas*. התחיל רבי
חייא rabbi chiya לדון *Hitchil Rabbi Chiya ladun*. נבילה לכל נאסרה *Neveilah
lechol ne'esra*. נבילה *Neveilah* was forbidden to all. כשהותרה במקדש *Keshehutrah beMikdash*,
when it was allowed in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*
by a bird קרבן *korban*, אצל כהנים הותרה *etzel kohanim hutrah*. It
was permitted by כהנים *kohanim*. לכהנים הותרה לא לזרים *Lekohanim hutrah, lo
lezarim*. For this guy who's a non-כהן *kohen*, it remains being a
נבילה *neveilah*. יש כאן משום זרות zarut. ויש כאן משום מליקה Melika
*Yesh kan mishum zarus veyesh kan mishum melikah*. התחיל בר קפרא bar
kappara לדון *Hitchil Bar Kappara ladun*. נבילה לכל נאסרה *Neveilah lechol ne'esra*.
כשהותרה במקדש כשהותרה במקדש הותרה *Keshehutrah beMikdash, keshehutrah beMikdash hutrah*. No, when
the Torah said this is how you bring a bird קרבן *korban*,
it basically said if you do it like this, it's not a
נבילה *neveilah*. So there actually, what בר קפרא bar kappara, *Bar Kappara*
says makes reasonable sense. Right? You could see all of these things
as being local questions, although it is interesting that they have it
in three places. But if I asked you, when you did the
case of the bird מליקה Melika *melikah*, right, is it a נבילה
*neveilah*, or does the Torah say if you do it this way
and you bring it as this type of a קרבן *korban*, it's
not a נבילה *neveilah*? It makes a lot of sense to say
it's not a נבילה *neveilah* which is מותר *muttar* to כהנים *kohanim*.
In this case, it's not a נבילה *neveilah*. Right? But again, so
that makes sense in this case. Lighting a match in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*, presumably we say
no, שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* still applies in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beis Hamikdash*. It's just a special allowance if you're doing the עבודה
avodah. *avodah*. Right? So there's different ways that you could come to
different conclusions in these cases. Is it you basically have the problem
but it's a special allowance for כהנים *kohanim* doing the עבודה avodah
*avodah* in the right way, or does the Torah say in this
case it's like the problem doesn't exist? Okay, but that what seems
to be the debate in these three cases, how do you conceptualize
it? כשהותרה במקדש הותרה אין כאן אלא ela משום זרות *Keshehutrah beMikdash
hutrah, ein kan ela mishum zarus*. So it seems like, as I
said, they are three parallel, but in a certain way local debates
about how you understand the nature of these allowances. Allowing טומאה בציבור
*tumah betzibur*, allowing עבודה avodah *avodah* on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, allowing eating
the dead bird. Do you understand it as if the problem doesn't
exist at all in these contexts, or it's a special allowance in
the context when you're a כהן *kohen* doing the עבודה avodah *avodah*
in the right way? And that would be the question, do you
get punished twice or only punished once? But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is going to interpret this to be about the question of both
two איסורים issurim *issurim*, does one איסור issur *issur* take effect on
the other איסור issur *issur*? Okay, so that's how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s going to reframe this. במאי קמיפלגי *Bemai kamifligi*? Yes.
Does everybody hold that מליקה Melika. *melikah* is not a type of
שחיטה *shechitah* and it produces a נבילה *neveilah*?
Well, that's exactly what we're asking. If it weren't in the context
of קרבן *korban* everybody would hold that, for sure. Right? So that's
exactly where the debate is. In the context of קרבן *korban*, how
do you conceptualize it? Is it a נבילה *neveilah* that's מותר *muttar*
for כהנים *kohanim* to eat, or is it not a נבילה *neveilah*?
That's exactly the question. Again, so I would have said it's a
local question. How do you conceptualize מליקה *melikah* of a bird when
it's done properly? But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say since
these are all three parallel debates, let's not look at them as
local debates, let's look at them as a larger question of איסור
חל על איסור issur chal al issur *issur chal al issur*. So
let's take a look. Top of ל"ג ע"א *lamed gimmel amud aleph*.
במאי קמיפלגי *Bemai kamifligi*? What's at the heart of this debate? באיסור
כולל kolel ואליבא דרבי יוסי *Be'issur kolel ve'aliba deRabbi Yosei*. It's a
question of איסור כולל issur kolel? *issur kolel* according to רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi. *Rabbi Yosei*. We're assuming רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi Yosei*,
who is prepared to say איסור חל על איסור issur chal al
issur, *issur chal al issur* by איסור מוסיף issur mosif *issur mosif*
as we saw before. Will he also say it by איסור כולל
issur kolel *issur kolel*? And these are cases of איסור כולל issur
kolel *issur kolel*. רבי חייא rabbi chiya, סבר savar רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yossi באיסור כולל kolel מחייב *Rabbi Chiya savar Rabbi Yosei be'issur kolel
mechayev*. רבי חייא rabbi chiya *Rabbi Chiya* says two by all these
cases. He's going to define all these cases as an איסור כולל
issur kolel *issur kolel* and say since רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Rabbi
Yosei* is the one who's prepared sometimes to say איסור issur חל
על איסור issur *issur chal al issur*, we'll say that he says
it even in a case of איסור כולל issur kolel *issur kolel*.
מחייב תרתי *Mechayev tartei*. In all these cases are איסור issur כולל
*issur kolel* and that's why you get two. בר קפרא bar kappara
סבר לא מחייב אלא חדא. lo mechayev ella chada. No, only one
even according to רבי יוסי. rabbi yosei ומאי איסור כולל איכא? u'mai
issur kolel ika? Where's the איסור issur כולל? הכא בשלמא זר מעיקרא
hacha bishlama zar me-ikara שרי במלאכה shari bemelacha ואסור בעבודה. v'assur ba-avodah.
So let's go in order. The case of a זר zar. that
does the עבודה avodah on שבת. Shabbos A זר, zar. initially, he
can do מלאכה melacha during the week, right? It's a Tuesday, he
can go ahead and light a match, but he can't do עבודה
avodah in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. אתיא לשבת, asya leShabbos, מיגו
דאיתסר migu d'kamitra במלאכה, bemelacha, איתסר mitra נמי nami בעבודה. ba-avodah. Since
he can't do other מלאכה, melacha, he also can't do the עבודה.
avodah So again, to use my, you know, איסור כולל איסור מוסיף
issur mosif. motif, right? איסור כולל is you broaden the כלל. klal.
Okay, so here's your זר. zar, Okay, here's your זר. zar Okay,
he is not allowed to do, right? Here, he is allowed to
do מלאכה. melacha. The one thing he can't do is עבודה avodah
in the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, that's what he can't do. עבודה avodah
in the מקדש. Mikdash. That's forbidden to him. Okay, okay. That's the
one thing that he can't do. Okay, comes along שבת, Shabbos, that's
on Sunday. Okay, this is on Sunday. He can't do עבודה avodah
in the מקדש. Mikdash. Comes along שבת, Shabbos. and שבת Shabbos says,
oh, now that it's שבת, Shabbos you know what else you can't
do? You can't do any of the ל"ט מלאכות. lamed-tes melachos. Okay,
right? So now has the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש, beis
hamikdash here we'll make a little, we'll make a little מזבח Mizbe'ach
here with a fire whatever. Okay, has the עבודה avodah in the
בית המקדש become forbidden to a broader scope of people? No. What's
happening is there's a wider class of things that cannot be done.
עבודה avodah. at all can't be done, which includes also the עבודה
avoda, in the בית המקדש. So this status hasn't broadened, which would
be מוסיף. mosif. The class of things that cannot be done has
broadened, and therefore because the ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tes melachos in general can't
be done, should that also say that that status also applies to
עבודה avoda in the מקדש? Mikdash?
It's now not only אסור assur from the perspective of עבודה avoda...
of a non-כהן, it's also אסור assur from the perspective of עבודה
avoda on שבת. Shabbos So איסור כולל is you either find yourself
now in a bigger population of people to whom this one איסור
applies, or this one person finds yourself...
No, bigger population of people is מוסיף. mosif. Okay, מוסיף mosif means,
if my visuals aren't helping, מוסיף mosif means more people are forbidden.
Okay, maybe this is an easier way of thinking it, it'd be
more a little more concrete. כולל means, okay, more activities are forbidden.
So in the case of the sister, right, becomes also the wife's
sister becomes brother's
wife, more people are forbidden. Right,
the scope of that of her status affects more people. Okay, other
brothers can't marry her. That's more people are forbidden. In the case
where brother's wife becomes wife's sister, more people aren't forbidden. He cannot...
cannot marry a wider range of people. He also cannot marry the
other sisters as well. So more activities are forbidden, not only... so
here, this is not forbidden on more people, that would be איסור
מוסיף. issur mosif. It's he can't do other things as well. He
also can't do ל"ט מלאכות lamed-tes melachos outside of the מקדש. Mikdash.
So I don't know if that helps to think about it as
that way, okay? The difference of מוסיף, mosif, it's more people, the
scope applies, it's a scope of larger people. Here it's a scope
of larger activities. But I actually think the difference is as that
this focuses on, if you would, the חפצא cheftza although we're talking
about people, the object that's forbidden and the object that's forbidden, its
scope has broadened. Okay, that's איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. This, the object
that's forbidden, be it a person, be it the עבודה avoda in
the מקדש, Mikdash, that scope has not broadened, but the person who
is prohibited now cannot do a wider range of things. Okay, so
this is broadening the scope of the חפצא cheftza and this is
broadening the activity of the גברא. gavra. Again, I'm using a lot
of different terms. If any of those help you, or if I'm
just confusing... it looks like I'm succeeding in confusing. No, I was
thinking about something else. Okay. You know in a sense, you're... anybody
who has... there's always an איסור מוסיף. mosif. This question's a little
bit ridiculous but you know, a זר, zar the day he's born
he's אסור assur to do the עבודה. avoda 20 years later, there's
a billion more people in the world. Yes, but that's... that's the
reverse of Michael's question of let's say there are no more sisters,
right? Then let's say there can't be more sisters, father and mother
are dead and so on. So it's all about conceptual, it's not
about practically whether there are things. Okay, so let's... let's see the
גמרא. Gemara Okay, that we get. בשלמא זר מעיקרא שרי במלאכה ואסור
בעבודה. bishlama zar me-ikara shari bemelacha v'assur ba-avodah. But בעל מום Ba'al
Mum מעיקרא me'ikara שרי shari באכילה. ba'achila. Now let's say you have
a כהן that has a מום. mum. So he's not allowed to
do the עבודה, avoda but he's allowed to eat the קרבנות. korbanot
ואסור ve'assur בעבודה. be'avoda. איתמלא itmalei he becomes טמא. tamei, מיגו migo
דאיתסר de'itessar באכילה ba'achila since now he can't he can't eat קרבנות
korbanot right because a בעל מום Ba'al Mum can eat קרבנות korbanot
but a טמא tamei. person cannot. איתסר itessar נמי nami בעבודה. be'avoda.
So that also now schleps along the עבודה avoda. as well okay
so replace עבודת בית המקדש avodat Beis HaMikdash and here you have
a case of if you are a בעל מום Ba'al Mum and
this was about... this was about... so בעל מום ba'al mum yeah
so he was אסור assur in עבודה... avoda okay so same point
a בעל מום ba'al mum. can't do the עבודה avodah but he
could eat קרבנות korbanot okay once he comes along and gets טמא
tamei now that he became טמא tamei, he can also not eat
קרבנות korbanot okay so since now this is a little bit different
because by the case of ל"ט מלאכות lamed tet melachot if you
did the עבודה avodah in the מקדש Mikdash you're both doing the
איסור עבודה issur avoda and the broader category of איסור מלאכה issur
melacha right here it's a little different because his status of becoming
טמא prohibited him from קרבנות korbanot from the eating perspective it also
is going to affect קרבנות korbanot from the doing perspective. You know
why is this a מיגו? migo? Why why why it's a little
different okay but the still point is now that you became טמא
your status vis-à-vis קרבנות korbanot has broadened okay it's true, it's in
terms of eating okay but you are now forbidden in קרבנות korbanot
in a way that you were not forbidden before and since you
are forbidden in קרבנות in a way that you were not before
you can't eat them you're also going to be forbidden in terms
of doing the עבודה avodah from that perspective as well. Is that
a general principle that someone who is אסור באכילה assur ba'achila is
אסור בעבודה? assur be'avoda? Yeah, generally yes because, yes because, assumed it's
an ontological construct, yeah, I'm not sure you have to say that
to make this logic work but generally that's true, that is true.
Okay anyway the גמרא Gemara says like this אלא ela that we
get we get how you can say כולל in both of those
cases אלא מליקה בבת אחת היא דמשכחת לה באיסור כולל לא משכחת
לה. ela Melika be'vas achas hi demishkachas lah be'issur kolel lo mishkachas
lah. But the גמרא gemara says מליקה you never get a sequence.
The כהן did מליקה right? This bird all of a sudden becomes
נבילה and it also becomes a קרבן that's אסור assur to זרים.
zarim. So in the very second that he became forbidden in this
bird he wasn't forbidden in the bird before מליקה I mean he
was it's an איסור מעילה issur me'ilah but the specific איסור of
a זר to eat a קרבן is only the moment it becomes
a קרבן. So the moment he does מליקה introduced two איסורים issurim
at the exact same time. The איסור of נבילה and the איסור
of a non-כהן eating a קרבן. So there's no sequence so what
could the debate be in that case? Okay so אי משכחת לה
באיסור כולל לא משכחת לה. hi demishkachas lah be'issur kolel lo mishkachas
lah. So can't be that they're debating the איסור with איסור כולל
because that could not apply to the case of מליקה. So let's
try again אלא fine let's say this is what they're debating קמיפלגי
באיסור בבת אחת. kamipalgi be'issur be'vas achas. They're debating what happens if
it happens at the same time can you get two איסורים issurim
if they're coming exactly at once? אליבא דרבי יוסי. aliba de'Rabbi Yossi.
And according to רבי יוסי rabbi yosei again רבי יוסי rabbi yosei
we know says you can get two איסורים issurim? if the second
one is מוסיף. What about if there's no second what about if
they're simultaneous would רבי יוסי rabbi yosei say you could get two
איסורים? issurin. רבי חייא סבר רבי יוסי באיסור בבת אחת מחייב תרתי.
Rabbi Chiya savar Rabbi Yossi be'issur be'vas achat mechayeiv tarti. If they
come at once you can be punished twice. ובר קפרא סבר לא
מחייב אלא חדא. u'Bar Kappara savar lo mechayeiv ela chada. Only one.
Now how do you get coming at once? The case of the
bird we said it comes at once as soon as it becomes
a נבילה it becomes a kosher קרבן and there's an איסור of
זרות. But how about these cases how do they come at once?
So the גמרא gemara says והכא מאי איסור בבת אחת איכא הכא.
ve'hacha mai issur be'vas achat
ika hacha. So זר ששימש בשבת zar she'shimmesh be'Shabbos if it's the
case of זר doing the עבודה on שבת Shabbos. right so we
already said before שבת Shabbos rolled around he was already אסור assur
in the עבודה. So where do you get him becoming אסור assur
in the עבודה and אסור assur on שבת shabbos at the same
moment right because Friday it wasn't both. So listen to the גמרא
gemara כגון דאייתי שתי שערות בשבת. kegon de'aysi shtei sa'arot be'Shabbos. He
became an adult on שבת. shabbos. Now you can't say he had
his Bar Mitzvah on שבת shabbos because that begins at the beginning
of the day actually maybe the גמרא gemara could. Maybe if he
turned thirteen at the beginning of the when שבת shabbos. came in.
I guess it could have said that too. But anyway, he got
his שתי שערות shtei sa'aros on שבת. So at the very moment
he became an adult, it was already שבת and he both couldn't
do the עבודה in the בית המקדש and he couldn't do מלאכה
melacha on שבת. So that's sort of like the questions you were
asking, דוד. dovid. So at that moment, that's the time when you
get both at the same time. Okay, so that's the answer to
that. Where are we? דהויה ליה זרות ושבת בהדי הדדי. d'havya leh
zarus v'shabbos bahadi hadadi. Now, בעל מום דמי, ba'al mum dami, how's
a case about a בעל מום that you get them both at
the same time? Okay. כגון דאפיק שתי שערות במום. kegon d'afik shtei
sa'aros b'mum.
He got two שערות, sa'aros, he had been טמא. He had been
טמא, but he wasn't yet an adult. And the moment that he
became an adult, that he got his two pubic hairs, he became
and he had a blemish, he became אסור assur both to do
the עבודה because he had a blemish and to do the עבודה
because he was טמא. So it happened at the exact same time
because when he became an adult, both of those things were current
statuses. Okay. דהויה ליה בעל מום וטומאה בהדי הדדי. d'havya leh ba'al
mum v'tumah bahadi hadadi. They come at the same time. אי נמי,
ee nami, or you could say, and this is a little bit
more of a fun case rather than having to rely on the
moment he becomes an adult, שחתך אצבעו בסכין טמאה. shechatach etzba'o b'sakin
tmeiah. He cut his finger with a טמא knife. So at the
very moment he became טמא, he became a בעל מום. Okay. So,
alright. You're off, right, exactly. Okay. So now we can create, construct,
again, it's not at all פשט pshat of the three cases. The
three cases seem to be much more general issues, but we can
now construct the scenario where all three of them are, where all
three cases happened at the same time. And we could say that's
the debate of רבי חייא rabbi chiya ובר קפרא, v'bar kappara, when
they happen at the same time, do you get two or do
you get one? So let's see what the גמרא gemara says like
this. בשלמא לרבי חייא, bishlama l'rabbi chiya, it works according to רבי
חייא, rabbi chiya כי אתני לדידיה. ki asnei l'didei. Now the גמרא
gemara is going to understand like this. How could it happen that
both רבי חייא rabbi chiya ובר קפרא v'bar kappara are taking opposite
oaths about what רבי rebbi said? I mean, רבי rebbi said one
thing. So it must be that somebody misunderstood. Now, you could also
say maybe רבי rebbi changed his mind, but the גמרא gemara doesn't
want to say that. It must be somebody misunderstood. So we're going
to try to reconstruct what could have happened to have to have
led to this misunderstanding. Okay, so let's take a look. בשלמא לרבי
חייא, bishlama l'rabbi chiya, according to רבי חייא, rabbi chiya I got
it, where scenario of בת אחת bas achas and he understood that
רבי rebbi said that you get two איסורים. So it makes sense
how בר קפרא bar kappara could have made a mistake. Why? כי
אתני לדידיה ki asnei l'didei אליבא דרבי יוסי, aliba d'rabbi yosei, because
when רבי rebbi taught this, said you get חייב chayav twice, so
he was saying according to רבי יוסי rabbi yosei. you get חייב
chayav twice. And that's why רבי חייא rabbi chiya heard you're חייב
chayav twice. כי אתני לבר קפרא, ki asnei l'bar kappara, when רבי
rebbi taught בר קפרא bar kappara and said you're only חייב chayav
once, אליבא דרבי שמעון, aliba d'rabbi shimon, he was teaching it according
to רבי שמעון rabbi shimon that you're only חייב chayav once and
there because רבי שמעון rabbi shimon generally holds that you don't say
אין איסור חל על איסור. ein issur chal al issur. So רבי
חייא rabbi chiya can understand the message he got and the mistake
בר קפרא made. אלא לבר קפרא, ela l'bar kappara, but according to
בר קפרא, he understands that רבי rebbi told him that according to
even according to רבי יוסי rabbi yosei. you only get once when
it's at the same time. So what did רבי rebbi חייא think?
רבי rebbi חייא heard twice. Where was he getting that idea? If
if בר קפרא thinks that רבי rebbi that רבי rebbi taught him
that even according to רבי יוסי rabbi yosei, it's only once, how
could what did he hear? No, רבי יוסי rabbi yosei is the
one who allows for the possibility of twice. Meaning רבי rebbi חייא
said, I heard from רבי rebbi you get twice, that was according
to רבי יוסי. rabbi yosei. I think where בר קפרא went wrong
is he probably heard when רבי rebbi was talking according to רבי
שמעון, rabbi shimon, according to רבי שמעון rabbi shimon it would be
only once. But בר קפרא says, no, I heard from רבי rebbi
twice and I believe that was according to I heard from רבי
once and I believe that was according to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
So then so then what did רבי חייא hear of twice, right?
There's no option according to you of twice. So the גמרא says
like this, אלא לבר קפרא רבי חייא שקורי קמשקר? ela l'bar kappara
rabbi chiya shikurei k'meshaker? Is רבי חייא lying? That he's swearing that
רבי said twice? I mean, again, it's so funny the גמרא asks
it this way, but the גמרא is taken by the fact that
they're taking oaths, so they really think what they're saying is, you
know, what they heard. So again, maybe the always answer always could
be he's not lying, he misheard, רבי changed his mind, but it
doesn't want to say that. It wants to explain what could have
led to the confusion. So the גמרא says אלא fine, we're not
arguing about בת אחת bas achas according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose
אלא כמפלגי באיסור בת אחת אליבא דרבי שמעון ela k'mipalgi b'issur bas
achas aliba d'rabbi shimon which makes sense. You know what? רבי יוסי
is prepared to say איסור חל על איסור even if it's sequential.
We're going to say that the question is רבי שמעון rabbi shimon
who normally holds אין איסור חל על איסור, ein issur chal al
issur, maybe he could hold it when it's at the same time
'cause then they're not competing, they're coming at the same time. So
it's the same thing we said before except we're saying the debate
is in רבי שמעון, rabbi shimon, not in רבי יוסי. And that'll
help in explaining how this error creeped in. Let's just read one
more sentence about this. באיסור בת אחת אליבא דרבי שמעון. b'issur bas
achas aliba d'rabbi shimon. בשלמא... bishlama... It now makes sense according to
Rabbi Chiyya קמשתבע לאפוקי לרבי שמעון מחזקיה. kamishtava l'apuki l'Rabbi Shimon me'Chizkiya.
So Rabbi Chiyya swearing and he's saying even though you think Rabbi
Shimon never holds of איסור חל על איסור, I'm going to swear
that you get twice even according to Rabbi Shimon because it's בבת
אחת. b'vas achas. אלא לבר קפרא למה ליה לאשתבועי? ella l'Bar Kappara
lamma lei l'ishtabuei? Why is he swearing? All Bar Kappara saying is
no, Rabbi Shimon just holds what he normally holds, you only get
חייב once. So you don't have to swear, I mean, that's a
normal opinion to hold, that's, you know, it's only חייב once. All
right, קשיא, kashya, that's difficult. But whatever, we're not going to get
hung up on that. I mean, everybody's excited, so everybody's swearing. Now
we're going to get back to our other question. בשלמא לבר קפרא,
bishlama l'Bar Kappara, now I get according to Bar Kappara where the
mistake crept in. He would say כי אתנייה רבי לדידי, ki asnaya
Rebbe l'didei, when Rebbe taught him once, אליבא דרבי שמעון, aliba d'Rabbi
Shimon, it was according to Rabbi Shimon. And now but he understands
where, where Rabbi Chiyya went wrong. כי אתנייה לרבי חייא, ki asnaya
l'Rabbi Chiyya, when Rebbe taught Rabbi Chiyya and Rabbi Chiyya heard twice,
that was אליבא דרבי יוסי. aliba d'Rabbi Yose. I can understand Rabbi
Chiyya where you went wrong. I understand you heard twice, but that
was according to רבי יוסי. We're talking here according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and I'm telling you Rebbe said according to רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon only once. So now you understand from Bar, from Bar
Kappara's perspective where Rabbi Chiyya went wrong. But we have now the
same question we had before except reversed. אלא לרבי חייא, ella l'Rabbi
Chiyya, but according to Rabbi Chiyya, he he thinks that Rabbi Shimon
taught him that Rebbe taught him according to Rabbi Shi- even according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon twice. So here how did Bar Kappara
hear once? אלא לרבי חייא בר קפרא שיקרי קמשקר? ella l'Rabbi Chiyya
Bar Kappara shikrei kamishaker? You think Bar Kappara is lying? Okay, so
we got, we have a way of explaining it that they're debating
what would be the status if it happened at the same time
either according to רבי יוסי or according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
But the problem is in either way of framing it, it's not,
you can't really explain how a mistake was made in both directions,
how either side could believe
the other side made a legitimate mistake. And we have to believe
it was a legitimate mistake, that it wasn't that Rebbe changed his
mind and
it wasn't that somebody misheard, it was a different type of a
context and that won't work in both directions. So we will pick
up and look at the answer for this tomorrow. All right.